it is my privilege and honor to ask you
to help me give a huge warm exciting
welcome to the source of this love G
Michael
[Applause]
[Music]
Roach love you thank you thank you thank
you
[Applause]
[Music]
hello
hi uh so we just finished a term in uh
our College our little College in
Sedona and uh I taught 72 classes in two
weeks
uh mostly translation classes and uh so
we we have a team of about uh it's about
120 translators uh about half of them
are in China uh so I'm training uh 80
well 80 translaters in China and then uh
we're trans we're training about 40
translators from America and Europe in
Sedona and uh so I brought the this is
two years of work how many pages uh you
were supposed to count
it I don't
know
2,747 pages of new new translations of
ancient books uh by this team uh in the
last two years so I thought during the
break if you get
bored uh you could come look at it and
uh we also had an interesting uh
negotiation uh with the Chinese
government because every time I go there
I I have to be interviewed by the
Security Bureau and uh I you know it's a
tough
process uh to teach there and uh so we
had a chance to meet with it there's a
new bank in China I guess Byron would
know uh called the Asian infrastructure
Investment Bank which was funded with a
100 billion dollars by the Chinese
government that's all the American bonds
that they own
uh seriously and they are uh rebuilding
the infrastructure of Asia and Europe so
they bought uh whole Railway systems the
Pakistani Railway systems Tibet is
connected to the ocean now and uh things
like that it's amazing it's huge thing
and uh so we had a meeting with them and
I said you need us you know and they're
like why and I said well you know you're
going to
go connect Europe to China basically
it's like the old Silk Road in fact it's
the same route and for 2,000 years there
was a Silk Road uh and there was a law
passed in ancient Rome against buying
Chinese
silk uh because all of Rome's gold was
going to uh
China and that was before Christ uh a
law was passed by the Roman senate and I
said you're going to get what do you
call it people kick back
no people are going to be resentful
after a while if you own all the
railways and ports and airports and you
know people are going to what's it
called uh
blowback anyway you're going to get
resentment from people and and you have
to learn to be a little more uh what do
you call
it interesting and
fun and uh diplomatic you know and you
know you have to so I have this idea
that you could take uh your ancient
culture and you could train your
Executives your business
Executives uh about your own ancient
literature and uh then you know my
experience in business in the diamond
business for 20 years was you know
diamonds are international everyone in
the every country has diamonds so when
you do the diamond business you who
interact with people from every country
every religion everybody has diamonds
and then the most interesting business
people were the ones who knew about
their history of their country and their
literature and their philosophy so I
said we'll train all of your business
Executives in your ancient literature
and then they'll be more they'll be more
interesting people and more fun people
and then when you take over the
world it'll be more
fun and so we had this conversation like
that and they said okay I'm we basic we
started a program uh called China soft
power and uh we we said look you have
hard power already you are the second or
first uh economy in the world and you
have probably the most powerful military
now but but do you have soft power you
see uh do you do you have cultural power
and and kindness and compassion and
things like that
so they said okay and and so we started
a program there's 40 uh business owners
big very big business owners and uh they
come I go three times a year we have
about a week together we spend all day
together and you know it's it's exciting
but the first couple days was rough
because they didn't know me I didn't
know them and uh so I was running off
the plane and the organizers asked me do
you have any materials ready I said
no uh I said I was too busy and they
said what are you going to do I said I
also don't
know and uh cuz in the first half of the
day I have to teach a uh translation
class so we found some ancient uh works
by Chinese
authors uh on the art of interpretation
for example so it would
take it would take eight ,000 pages of
English it would take about 30 years to
translate and so we started it and we
started with a group of 80 translators
and we're working our way through it so
that's the first half of the day that
I'm supposed to go meet with all these
Chinese business Executives and sell
them on their own
culture but I don't have anything ready
so I sent them a message I said everyone
has to come to the translation class and
it's very
obscure translations which if you have
the courage to look inside you will see
and uh very very difficult texts uh and
uh so they
came and uh I said okay you have to sit
here for four hours and listen to
ancient literature your ancient
literature of your country and then you
have an assignment in the afternoon this
is how I got out of teaching a class I
said you have an assignment in the
afternoon uh to work in teams which
Chinese people do really really well
and so teams of 10 guys each 10 women or
men and these are Big Business very big
business owners and and you're going to
create uh modern
applications from the ancient literature
you heard
translated and that's your that's your
training that's what you have to do
because that's all I do you know we
started in New York uh I don't know
1905 or something right
wig 1905 uh and the idea was I had just
been to the gashi course or I was
finishing my gishi degree and that's 20
years of training in five great uh
subjects and uh so I thought it would be
cool to teach it to westerners you know
and but I had to make it interesting to
Modern people so I was struggling to
take the parts of the gy course that
makes sense to anyone which is not all
of it and we created uh 36 courses it's
about I think it's almost 20,000 pages
of translation and uh so Hector's taught
the whole thing through here uh John
Stillwell taught it all through uh will
me has been to
it 18 coures he's on his third time
through uh the three jwes is going to
start a review of it this year the next
year and then they're going to go
Advanced uh then they're going to do the
advanced ones so anyway
uh you know so my contribution was to
take the ancient gesi course and
modernize it and make it available to uh
normal people and at the time it was a
big deal and we got a lot of
criticism I got a lot of criticism for I
told somebody today uh for teaching
women the gishi course because they
weren't allowed to see the gishi course
uh before that no woman was allowed to
be a Gish for a thousand
years and uh so it was I got a little
bit of
heat on that uh and recently the first
official woman gishi was uh
recognized uh by the
authorities but we did it 20 years
before uh it seems to go like
that uh but
anyway so these Chinese business people
I said look uh because our courses are
famous in China many many people do our
courses many thousands of people which
in China is nothing
but uh you know it's a lot and I said
I'm teaching you my secret you see
you're going to go to a translation
class you're going to hear your ancient
books and then you're going to figure
out something that can be used in your
Modern Life or your modern business
you're going to do I'm teaching you what
I do and that's all I do that's my big
secret you know that's why I'm I get to
travel around the world you know and
teach 30,000 people year the reason is
all I do is take an ancient book and
find something cool and then teach it to
business people for some kind of
application in business you see so I
told these guys I'm teaching you what I
do this is the secret then you can
replace me you know that's basically all
I do I take some ancient wisdom and uh
translate it and then I dig around I
call it diamond
mining and we call it diamond mining now
so I dig around I try to find something
cool that we can use for your Modern
Life okay so that's all I do and and I
taught them what I do and they got very
good at it scare scary good at it you
know and then now uh the first group
it's 18 months training for Chinese
executive
uh they came to me a few months ago and
said we're teaching the second
group we'll take we'll take it you know
and I'm
like okay and because they're good
they're really really good at it you
know so anyway I was in I taught 72
classes two weeks ago it was exhausting
you know it was incredibly exhausting CU
each class takes about maybe four or
five hours to prepare and uh so we are
translating these ancient books and I
thought I would teach you the cream of
of what we did okay and uh so I'm going
to do it
tonight uh I'm going to start I'm going
to start on the cream of the cream okay
and then uh those of you who work for
three jewels or work at three jewels
will'll do another course tomorrow
evening at the three jewels but because
the space is
limited uh the second half of this talk
uh tomorrow uh if you're not a staff
member at the three jws or something
like that you're welcome to listen
online okay because that we we crushed
as many people as we could in but I
think it's G to you know they can't take
more they informed me a couple weeks ago
just not to talk about
it so of course I'll talk about it but I
but I negotiated they're going to put it
online so if you want tomorrow night
it'll be live streamed okay this second
half of of this class and then in the
morning or lunch breakf
brunch uh we'll do uh we'll also do some
cool stuff uh that's the people who paid
for tonight to make it free uh we
invited them to lunch tomorrow so I'll
do a
special stick for them okay uh so
tonight I'd like to do uh the cream of
the cream uh we're working on 108 books
uh a series of eight books and um my
favorite lately okay it changes every
few months but uh my favorite lately is
Nina so I'll talk about narina and then
we're gonna dive into narina okay so
narina is sometimes called Buddha Number
Two uh second Buddha to walk in this
world uh the Buddha lived 500
BC uh you know and was enlightened here
in this world 500 BC 2 and a half
thousand years ago
and then uh he taught for I think he was
81 years old when he passed away 8080 81
and uh he taught constantly throughout
his life we have uh we have uh
990 uh texts based on his teaching
survive and there's a rumor that there
are thousands more that were lost okay
then he passed away and then there was a
grand meeting of all his students and uh
they say 500 uh of his
students and uh they agree kind of they
messed things up okay I reminds me when
I left New
York just
kidding so I I taught all the courses
here and then I went into a three-year
silent Retreat you know and I thought oh
you know I don't know what's going to
happen actually they they kept it very
well and uh they they did everything
very well they kept it quite well but
after the Buddha died they didn't keep
it very well and this meeting I guess
there was too many people there it was
kind of a committee which is a bad way
to do
religion and uh they they had a big
committee and they they wrote out the
teachings and that record is called Abid
Dharma and I did Abid Dharma for 12
years uh I translated the main text for
12 years that was my first thing in the
monastery and it is the most born dry
subject in the universe extremely dry
and boring and uh so for 700
years uh this school took over called
Abid Dharma and the boring
school and uh so Buddhism got very dry
and and I appreciate it because I worked
on it for 12 years I memorized most of
it and uh it's long
like that goes on like
that and uh then came the gar okay 200
ad uh I think he might have been
influenced by uh Christianity I'm not
sure uh Judaism
reached the Malibar Coast the west coast
of
India uh before Christ and then uh
Thomas the disciple Thomas was sold uh
into slavery as a carpenter to work in
uh the Tibetans call it
dook uh what's it called in
uh
Afghanistan uh I
forget no there's a city anyway he was
uh it's a beautiful story you want to
know the story okay this a beautiful
story uh
and it's told in the uh Gospel of Thomas
as it survives in
Syria and uh so you know Jesus appeared
to his
disciples after he died and uh gave them
all a mission you know Peter went to
Rome and other guy went to Greece and
you know then came the Catholic church
and the Eastern or Orthodox church but
he also assigned Thomas to go to India
there would have been three Christian
branches uh except Thomas refused to go
so he asked Thomas to go to India and
Alexander had just gotten back you know
300 years be well he didn't come back he
died because it was the end of the world
so Thomas is like I don't want to go to
the end of the world and Jesus is like
you're a signed to the end of the world
and he says look I'm a Jew I speak
Hebrew you know he says I don't care
just go you know and he appeared to him
in his bedroom and Thomas refused to go
and uh
so then there was a slave trader uh from
what is that place come on Northern
Afghanistan F it's where AA
studied sounds like tashk but it's not
anyway huh look it up
huh
no no Afghanistan side anyway I'll think
of it by the end
uh
so then uh this slave Traer came to
Jerusalem and he was probably it was in
a Starbucks I think and uh Jesus had
just died all his disciples are laying
low and uh trying to keep out of trouble
and then Jesus appears and talks to the
slave
trador and he they're sitting in a
coffee shop if you've ever been to
Jerusalem one of these small streets
and uh the GU Jesus saidwell what who
what are you looking for and he says I
need a carpenter who knows Greek style
cuz Thomas was an expert in in the Greek
style the Jews knew the Greek style and
they were popular
slaves so uh so
they Jesus says I have a guy for you you
know he's he's perfect he's a carpenter
his name is Thomas you know and uh the
slave trader says okay uh can I meet him
and and then Thomas is just walking down
the street and and and Jesus says I own
him he's my man you know and he says
well how much is it going to cost he
says the 20 pieces of
silver and the guy says well he must not
be very good because 20 pieces of silver
is almost nothing and then Jesus said A
A man should not be sold for more than
his
master because Jesus was sold I think
for 30 pieces of silver so the guy's
like what are you talking about he says
well never mind and
uh and then he and the guy gets
suspicious he says are you really the
guy's owner are you his master and he
says yeah yeah he's my slave you know so
there's this beautiful scene uh where
Thomas walks down the street sees Jesus
at the coffee shop walks in to say hi
this is after the
crucifixion and uh he's all excited and
he's like you know oh Jesus it's you and
and Jesus says uh this is my friend you
know his name was Hamas or something and
uh and the and the slave trader says is
this guy your master and Thomas says my
only Lord and
Master took him to
India uh took him to
Afghanistan and that's a long beautiful
story uh but it was just before nagaj
and and Thomas ended up uh after he got
out of
prison uh because he didn't build the
palace properly which is another
beautiful
story uh but I believe he affected South
India he he he was martyred in Chennai
Madras he died in Madras and uh I
believe he
affected Buddhism uh but there's some
beautiful
stories of uh Buddhist monks meeting the
Greek Kings who succeeded Alexander one
named menander
menander that the in Sri Lanka they call
Melinda and the great teaching on
emptiness the greatest early teaching on
emptiness is a conversation between a
Buddhist monk named
nagasena and the greatek King Melinda
menander and uh so I think there was
this big connection going on so anyway
Nar came out of that 100 years later Nar
appeared in South India and he hungered
for the original teachings uh of the
Buddha that had been uh B Bor
bized made
boring uh he he he he hungered for the
deeper teachings and he felt like
something was missing and uh so he
started writing uh poetry about
emptiness and uh it said that he was uh
had seen emptiness directly which is
very rare and uh so in sometimes he's
called the Arya which means a person who
has seen emptiness directly he's just
called the Arya you know and and he
wrote poetry about emptiness and he
revived we would say the original
teachings of Lord Buddha 700 years later
and that came to be called the the
greater way the Mahana and specifically
the middle way Maj Maka and so what I
thought tonight uh he wrote uh six
famous books of poetry and uh we are
translating a lot of them and
commentaries on them in in the college
and I thought uh it's just uh seems very
beautiful to me uh he's a extraordinary
writer I think it's a thing about Aras
people who have seen empist directly
that they are
uh they're so different
Arya means different Evolution from us
they're so different that uh the way
they write is very very uh I don't know
how to say it it's like super
genius but they love to do things short
and sweet and profound and so I thought
uh we go for a dip in the
Gara uh tonight uh with your permission
i' I'd like to go there and what's
striking me as we work through the
translations uh all over the world and
we're training you
know 120 translators uh by the way we
also have a secondary translation
team uh they are translating the
translations into uh Russian I think we
have a lady here Maria kraa from Moscow
where are
you there uh and German her husband uh P
the Val
Myrtle uh is helping to do the German UT
sharf is helping to do the
German uh
Spanish uh from many different people
but we have Mexico crew here three
great wise people the M Los Mo Los muis
they have a radio show uh like a the
guardian of radio show once a
week twice a week it's like the hottest
thing in gu
and they've been doing it for five years
or something three years three years
like super
hot uh live nage on the on the radio we
have a Syrian here nor ibraim she's
translating into Arabic uh we have uh
Ben's not here right he's doing
French and we have Indonesian and things
like that so if you're interested uh to
help with that uh you're very welcome
okay so talk to
Tim or nor nor is
okay yeah and uh we have here the people
who find the original text uh John Brady
you should give him a hand can you stand
[Applause]
up uh he's been going around the world
for about 30 years finding the ancient
text to input uh he they cataloged
141,000 books in Russia St Petersburg
took 14 years they're working
on how many
Christina 500,000 between 250 and
500,000 they're working together as a
team there in Mongolia we started 15
years
ago we're about a quarter way through or
something like that maybe and Via FAS
working on the Sanskrit we stand up in
[Applause]
uh so anyway I thought I would tonight
take out the sweetest things from the
translations but if you'd like to
participate uh in any way we need uh
secondary translators of
Tor uh people who can translate the
English or Russian or whatever you like
and uh uh we also need people to help us
fundraise uh because it's expensive it
costs about I don't
know close to a million dollars a year
to to do the whole thing so if if you'd
like to help with that project talk to
nor you want to stand up or Tim okay and
uh the the idea is we'll print
108 rare books uh of the most important
cream of the cream which you will learn
tonight
and then uh it'll be translated into I
don't know 15 languages and it will take
about a 100 years uh some of the books
are scheduled to take 20
years uh to translate so we need help if
you'd like to help in any way uh talk to
those guys
okay uh or Rachel three juls you guys
you want to stand them yeah the the
three jeles people yeah
oh Stephen I didn't see or Stephen talk
to
them uh we need help uh translating and
we need help
uh uh fundraising so but the fundraising
is fun you just join a team and they
tell you what to do and don't worry
about it okay so please help I I think
it
will this the last time this was was
done in was in 700 AD by uh a similar
team of crazy people uh in China and uh
it's kind of a
repeat of that but what happened in
China is it changed the country for a
thousand years
so I think it will happen here okay
let's go to
narina uh there's a nice carving
oh okay there's a photo on the front of
your reading
okay and uh I have a advisor who's been
helping me since he was a small kid and
now he's a big kid where Francis where
are
you oh can you explain what's this photo
on the
front yeah part of a comet airplane okay
so this is an
airplane uh it was by the the the H the
havin company in ger in Britain
after the war and they made the first
jet passenger plane okay four
engine uh Jet Plane first one for
passengers in the world and it had four
uh it had four engines and they for to
make it pretty they put them in the
wing and uh you know I don't know if you
know the story anyway they flew for a
while six months the queen flew on it uh
the princess flew on it and then they
started to fall
down and it was a little disturbing and
uh Wings would fall
off and you know people would nobody
survived so nobody knew exactly what
happened but uh there are stories that
like in Rome two two crashed in Rome in
the in in the period of six months and
one of them crashed without its wings on
and uh you know you're talking like 150
normal people like us sitting on the
plane and suddenly it breaks in half and
everyone died so nobody knew what
happened so they would collect the parts
together one one crashed over the
Mediterranean they had to collect the
parts from underwater and they would
took them to England and they put them
back together and tried to figure out
what happened and there what happened
was that there were small
cracks the windows were
Square uh and small cracks would develop
at the corner of the window and people
were just like okay there's a little
crack in the window it's okay it's not a
big thing uh but then the metal fatigue
would start in that corner and then
eventually the planes would just break
in half uh halfway through the
flight uh and then came this uh custom
of people starting to watch for
cracks uh on airplanes and testing with
special x-rays to see if there's cracks
uh in the airplane people got interested
in
cracks uh mini what do you call Micro
cracks that they weren't interested in
before uh because the planes were flying
down all over the world the first
passenger airplanes with jet engines and
uh and finally they figured out what was
happening okay and then all the people
who had said all the cracks are
nothing uh you know they came
unpopular and uh especially with the
families of the dead people and uh the
the lesson is that we got to look for
cracks okay if you see cracks you got to
pay attention Okay I was on a flight
from Dallas to
guara recently and it was a hot day in
July and uh we we're taxiing out to the
runway slowly and I'm looking out the
window and there's jet fuel pouring off
the wing like huge gallons and gallons
of jet fuel pouring off the wing you
know and I'm like
and they're about to take off and I said
should I scream you know should I say
something or should I just it's not very
cool uh to start screaming just before
take off you know and then I so I I just
decided not to say
anything and then I said you're so
stupid if you die cuz you're afraid to
scream that's so stupid I said yeah
that's stupid so I yelled I said hold it
you know and everyone's like security
people you I said hold it stop the plane
you know and they're all like what you
know and the stus came over and said
look out the window and there's gallons
and gallons of Jeff field pouring out
off the wing and she says that's
probably nothing you know I said could
you ask someone you know could you just
ask someone you know and then that she
went and got the co-pilot they stopped
the plane and the co-pilot came back and
he's like hm it's probably nothing you
know I'm like do you know it's nothing
no could you ask somebody you know I
said okay we'll ask somebody and then
they called the what do you call the air
Tower and all that and it is normal uh
when the plane gets hot and the fuel
expands there's an emergency valve and
it dumps fuel out on the runway hundreds
and hundreds of gallons of fuel I don't
know what they
happens to it if you spark or something
but but it it's interesting and we took
off and I'm still
here uh but sometimes you notice
something is wrong and this is a theme
with Nagina okay because I've been
eating narina heavy for the last few
years and uh we've been deep deep into
Nagina and he keeps saying don't you
notice the cracks don't you notice
something weird going on and after a
while you don't notice it you know
you're like y okay n gar just calm down
it's probably all right you know but
he's insistent you know and he keeps
saying something's weird something's
going on you know and there's a cracks
in the airplane or there's some kind of
weird stuff going on you know
something's not right okay so I thought
I would follow that theme uh through
several of his books that we're working
on one is called Rena
ratnavali which means a string of
precious jewels and then has another
book called
wisdom which is the most famous book on
emptiness ever written and it's the
source of everything everything since
then and We're translating the best
commentary uh to that two of them uh one
by
tonapa which is a take about 20 years
we're about uh six years into it and uh
and so we're and then the third one is a
book called the verses on
reasoning uh and these are all three
three of his six famous books on
emptiness okay so what I did was it's
like a what do you call Whitman sampler
chocolate I thought you'd enjoy some
chocolate from the G okay so here we go
uh first verse and there's my favorite
picture of
him okay he
uh by his time many of the Original
Scriptures were
missing and he figured out that the
dragons had some of them because dragons
like sparkly precious things and there
used to be dragons uh just like in The
Lord of the Rings okay and they really
do like uh sparkly things like crows uh
so they collect
sutras and uh he and there's a long
story but he went to the land of the
dragons and he recovered to sutras and
as a
result he's a monk right monk Baldhead
whenever it was hot in India the dragons
would cover his
head and Dragon called Naga right arj
means Lord so Naga arj means lord of the
dragons and he would uh boss them around
okay he had some special power over them
so you see when you see a picture of
ngago you know it's him because the
snakes are above his head holding out
their hoods to protect him it's a what
do you call it
what's that cream you put on when
it's sunscreen ancient
sunscreen okay nag so here's uh one of
his most famous verses okay the person
is not their solidness nor their wetness
nor their warmth nor the motion inside
nor the space within nor even the
awareness of the world not all of these
get nor all of these together and how
could you find them somewhere else so
this is a reference to the ancient
medical terms of the four elements or
the five elements okay s say
sa come on don't be New York
okay
CH okay uh sometimes four sometimes five
sometimes six elements okay and uh this
is like Aristotle or Socrates and we
think they're kind of
crude descriptions of medical terms
right they didn't have you know
esophagus and I don't know large
intestine small that they had the
elements and if you understood the
elements you could treat disease uh so
you know
most modern people think they were just
stupid they didn't have microscopes you
know we're not really made of the five
elements but if you study it more in
that most boring book called
Abida uh you find out that there are
quite sophisticated descriptions of the
basic energies of the universe like
gravity or electricity or mass or you
think it's very very sophisticated so
warmth solidness means uh it's called
Earth element so I I translated it as
solidness it's because it's not uh dirt
inside your body it's the uh what do you
call it
solidity in your body it's the bones
it's the it's the stuff in the bones
that keeps you upright right now that
keeps your neck holding your head it's
not uh it's not that they believed there
was little pieces of dirt in you it's
not that they were uh what do you call
stupid or something they were Advanced
it's the principle it's the quality of
solidity in the human body it keeps your
skin on it keeps your head up it keeps
you walking okay otherwise you'd be like
a jelly fish okay that's what solidity
ises s that's Earth element okay true
water element is the wetness in your
body okay so there's a certain amount of
wetness in steel also according to the
ancient teachings there's a some wetness
in this 100 years from now this will be
drier than it is now there are there are
small amounts of water even in a piece
of iron okay and they they cause
fluidity okay they are fluidity they're
like gravity okay
satu fire is warmth but compared to
absolute zero so it's not some stupid
thing that the Ancients like Aristotle
thought you had some fire inside your
body and if it got too little you got
sick or something like that it's not
that it's the quality of
warmth Above So ice has some warmth in
it you can make ice colder you see what
I mean so it still has some warmth in it
so it's it is the quality of heat okay
uh inside your body it's life you know
when you die you get cold
colder and as the years go by the pieces
get all colder and colder okay so you
have you have this quality of warmth it
the steel has warmth ice has warmth okay
the Sun has more okay so we all have
worm
sat uh they call motility what do I call
it motion okay you move right we did a
yoga class today with Coco was really
nice especially the
ending just kidding uh but the fact that
you can move your body that the heart
beats that the lungs move that the legs
can move is uh motion you have motion
your body has motion so you are made of
solidity you are made of water you are
made of warmth you are made of motion
and you are made of the space in which
these
things sit which we're going to talk
about later okay and you have awareness
okay you think you're aware of the world
okay these are the basic parts to a
human being he could have said arms
legs head and brain and some people do
that that but he's
cool you know he's staying on an atomic
level uh you have mass you have momentum
you have inertia you have grav you know
it's very deep uh ancient ideas uh that
you are made this is what you are made
of you are made of
energies you are made of five or six
energies okay and then he says but
you're
not okay but you're not and uh and then
he says but you're not made of anything
else either okay got it you are not made
of What You're Made Of
individually each part is not you all
the parts
together is not you and you're not
anything else either okay and he says
something weird going on you should have
notied cracks you should notice that
something weird is going on then we're
like what do you mean
you know what do you mean I'm not all my
parts together what do you mean he says
well what happens when you cut your arm
off does Michael are you less Michael if
you get your arm amputated are you how
many arms you got to lose to not be
Michael anymore you see how much of
Michael can you lose before you lose
Michael there's a problem right is
Michael this
paper cuz if if you come up here and say
this is the most stupid paper I've ever
read it's going to hurt
Michael Michael thinks it's part of
Michael you see what I mean uh the seat
somebody takes your seat in the
break you know no you try to take a baby
from a mother and say this is not part
of you you see can another person be
part of you oh can can me extend to
another person the guardian is trying to
say weird stuff is going on your idea of
you is a little bit strange you know uh
I had a guy uh I have friends here from
New Jersey I spent uh I don't know how
many 25
years in a small Mongolian Temple right
and uh we had a Mongolian guy named
ruj uh old man his name was rubor I I'll
give a $500 anyone who can tell me what
the Sanskrit
is okay cancel that
uh huh
sauti uh the hero of uh some book The
Diamond Cutter Sutra okay it's the
corrupt uh Tibetan which is uh D
dup but anyway it got corrupted in
Mongolian
so I used to take care of him I used to
give him his insulin shots you know he
needed insulin shots every day
and I I asked the doctor you know I said
the doctor said you're going to give him
the shots and I said I don't know I
don't know how to give a shot so he gave
me an orange he said poke the orange and
shoot it three or four times and I did
he says okay now you're
trained and uh and then I gave him his
uh shots every day and then he got a
sore on his foot right and
uh which is very dangerous for a
diabetic right and then he put so the
ancient Mongolian treatment the comic uh
treatment is to put horse pee on it uh
which made it much worse and uh he so so
we went to the doctor and I'm
translating for
him uh and the doctor says You must cut
the foot off this week you must or you
will die it has Garing you know and I'm
translating you know we got to cut the
foot off this week and he's like no and
I'm like you're going to die he says
okay
I'll die you know and I'm like the
doctor says you're going to die you need
to cut the foot off he says I won't cut
the foot off cuz it's me you
see it won't be me if you cut my foot
off you see what I mean this is very
neaga he's like if I cut my foot off I
won't be root door anymore I won't be
suby anymore you know can cannot do you
know I don't care die die you know and
uh so they put him in a special uh
nursing home with what do you call it uh
hospice and um we said goodbye and you
know then I got busy my llama got busy
we were taking care of him so he was all
taken care of like 15 years later we go
to the nursing home he's still
there you know and he looks at me
like if I don't cut the foot off I'll be
dead right and I'm like I'm so sorry you
know and he's and he looks at me like I
felt so bad I said look I was just
translating you know and uh and I said
you know this is like most amazing
you're Gang Green he should be dead
right and I said what' you do he
said and I'm like but you see he thought
that if he lost his foot he wouldn't be
himself anymore okay got it so the
guardian is saying something weird is
going on who is Connie who is John is
John Connie is John Connie a couple they
going to change their name from O'Brien
and Brady to o' Brady I heard and uh at
at one point can you take away a baby
and the mother won't fight you as if it
were them you see or at what point can
you cut your foot off and you are still
root door right so the guardian is just
saying it's a little weird you know who
we think is me is a little weird you
know cuz you can take off an arm and
you're still Michael right and you can
when you have a child when you give
birth to a child or your child gives
birth to a child
right like your daughter just
did uh it becomes part of you you know
try to take that child away try to hurt
that child and that Mom will fight you
uh like anything you see what I mean so
narian is saying it seems to be a little
weird of who is you who is me you see
how much of you is you can you remove an
arm and you're still you yes can you add
a baby and and then you get fatter you
become double and yeah you do you see
you can
cover the baby with me and you can
reduce Me by an arm and you're still me
you see so what is me it's me all your
parts it's not okay because you can take
parts off you can add parts and you're
still you you see that's a crack in the
plane try to appreciate it something
weird is going on you see what I mean
when you have a kid the kid is a
different person you know somebody tries
to hurt your baseball star son uh you're
GNA do something right cuz your self got
bigger the guardian is saying yourself
is elastic Orie is elastic ory can cover
more than Orie or ory can cover less
than o if oi gets gang green on his leg
you see and he says it's weird it's just
a little weird you know who are you who
is you you see are you your arm or not
no are you your body no why not it's
Michael's body you see that means
Michael's separate from the body got
it got it it's my body it's the body of
Michael right that means Michael is
separate from the body right isn't
it it doesn't make sense the guardian
saying what Michael's mind wait Michael
is the mind no Michael's the one who has
the mind you see Michael's the one who
has the body you can lose a piece of
your body and you're still Michael okay
so therefore the body is not Michael
otherwise when you cut the foot off and
you throw in the garbage Michael got
thrown in the you understand
try to understand something weird is
going on okay something's wrong okay uh
you are not your body because you say
Connie's Connie's hair needs fixing you
know you stand there we all stand there
some of us it takes less time right John
and uh we comb our hair you know and we
say that's Michael's hair but when you
say the hair of Michael it means it's
not Michael you see what I mean or
Michael's mind so if Michael has a mind
and Michael has a body it's like Michael
has a book and Michael has shoes but
Michael's not the book and Michael's not
the shoes got it so if Michael can have
a body and Michael can have a mind then
who's
Michael it's weird something's
happening oh guess it's just a crack in
the window no big
thing uh what's it say I was so happy
1946 or something they said origin of
failure okay origin of failure guess why
I chose
that if you don't figure out the Michael
thing and your leg and your arm and your
friend and your baby if you don't figure
out who you are origin of
failure okay you will fail in life okay
you will fail in life and if you figure
it out
about the cracks you become incredibly
successful okay we had the fast I
believe it's the fastest
growing Industrial company in Manhattan
in history Diamond our Diamond company
in history it doubled every 18 months
for 19
years double the
employees for 19 years every 18 months
if you have 500
employees you know hire 500 more every
18 months then the next 18 months hire a
thousand and imagine that you know
imagine that going on for for 19 if you
figure out uh the origin of
failure there's something about uh
Michael and the pieces of Michael that
you have to figure out if you figure it
out uh you can do anything okay you can
do anything we have 3,000 people came to
the event in
Taipei you know it's weird we started in
in uh where was that place Hell's
Kitchen with five people around a
kitchen you were there or you were
close uh it's weird if you figure it out
you can do stuff you can do cool stuff
okay you can make millions of dollars
you can build a college for $5 million
JB uh built it said build a college we
didn't have any money zero now we have
this beautiful college it's paid for
okay people sit there and study
you know if you figure out
the the cracks thing uh your whole life
changes then you can fly to LA and not
fall down okay uh I'm trying to say if
you don't figure out the thing about
Michaels
leg uh you will never be successful and
you will keep having crashes and and you
will not understand why you see there's
something about this question
which your whole life depends on if you
understand it you can have you can make
anything happen in your life and if you
don't understand it you will continue to
have origin of failure you see no matter
what you try to do business or or or
personal
relationships stuff will go wrong and
your plane will crash
regularly uh every five years every 10
years your plane will crash okay and if
you figured out
tonight then just cool stuff happens to
you over and over you know Jigme does my
uh what do you call it account thing G
like your bank account's like insane I
said give it away she's like yeah but it
keeps coming back you
know okay let's just right we just
did something orange did you hear about
that come
on okay anyway uh okay let's go on if
you figure out the source of failure if
you figure out the emptiness of
you uh you can do weird stuff you can be
happy all the time and everything you do
is successful okay if you don't figure
it out your plane will continue to fall
down it sure you sure over and over and
your your airplane will fall down okay
got it let's go to the next one what
time uh anybody
have what time is it I'm giving you a
break okay don't say I didn't give you a
break and we do have Refreshments uh and
I will sign books outside and if you
can't afford a book I'll give you a book
guess why okay
uh the next page says understand every
living being in the same way you
understand yourself understand every
existing thing in the same way you
understand beings this is the Lord
Buddha very very very famous statement
about emptiness if you figure out the
emptiness of you of John of Connie of
Bera or
Bera uh if you figure it out then
everything becomes clear okay so we're
going to go uh you got that chart for me
Tim where is that this is part of a
teaching we give in in other
countries um this is an outline of all
the things in the universe this is very
famous very famous teaching by uh
dharmakirti okay a very
fundamental teaching of dharmakirti U
this is all the stuff in the in the
universe we're going to go through all
our stuff in the universe Box by box
okay and we're going to point out the
cracks that something's weird is going
on something's not right okay and you
can ignore the cracks Gula I don't
really care whether my foot is part of
me or not right now it's part of me
that's okay I'm not stressed about it
and I'm telling you you got to figure it
out because if you figure it
out uh if if you if you admit something
weird is going
on uh and you find out how to fix it uh
you can have a Jet Plane you see what I
mean that goes around the world you see
you can do anything if you figure it out
and if you keep ignoring the
discrepancies the weird stuff the cracks
you will always be unhappy stuff will
always fail okay I'm trying
to this is Nara okay so we're going to
go through all this stuff One By One The
Blue Box
means uh this is the definition of
existence in Buddhism Andy you have
that m
okay
say the definition the definition of
existence is anything you can perceive
okay in Buddhism that's the definition
of existence then your mind should go to
the tree in the forest if a tree falls
in the forest and nobody hears it did it
fall down what's the Buddhist
answer huh someone always sees
everything why cuz you can develop your
mind to see all things you see there are
people who see all things the Sanskrit
word for a person who sees all things is
a Buddha okay so anyway uh anything you
can perceive and you're not drunk and
you're not crazy and you're not totally
jealous at the
moment uh is real okay so that's reality
okay it's divided into two parts and
we're going to follow it here we're
going to do
the left side is things that exist and
change okay things that change in the
world okay all the stuff that changes
what percent of stuff
changes
99.999999 okay uh and and Moment by
moment
say
k
CH definition of
impermanence uh in and out of existence
moment Instant by instant 65 times as
finger snap things go in and out of
existence okay that's the stuff on the
left okay three basic categories of the
stuff on the left bottom left box is
called physical stuff okay and the Abid
Dharma this sleepy
book says that you spend most of your
life in the
visual Arena of physical things about
90% of your total experience
is things you can see okay and then uh
I'm going to go to
narina pointing out the cracks of
physical stuff okay so we have a
feeling and science has taught us since
you were a kid that stuff is made of
little
pieces okay and you know in my time it
was
atoms and the world was made of atoms
you see and atom comes from Sanskrit uh
a means
not uh it's the called the privative a
it comes at the beginning of the word it
comes in
atheistic or uh agnostic or apathetic
and it means not okay uh uh means not t
means
divisible it's an ancient Sanskrit route
parts of the town that were set aside
from the town for worship were called
Temple
okay Temple came from that so atam means
cannot be split further cannot be
divided in the modern times in physics
it means when you split that thing one
more time it doesn't act the same
anymore okay so you take an atom of
something an element right element means
that and I I put the periodic chart of
the elements here you know what the word
element means is if you have a an atom
or a molecule of oxygen for example and
you split more if you split the hydrogen
from the oxygen in water it doesn't act
like water anymore okay so there are
smaller parts nobody says that
hydrogen doesn't have smaller pieces but
if you break it into smaller pieces it
won't act like hydrogen anymore and
that's why we call it an atom okay a so
you can't break it for you can
you can hit it in a nuclear what do you
call
collider something accelerator and you
can break it into pieces but those
pieces won't act like hydrogen anymore
you see I mean so that that's what an
atom means okay so there's a smallest
piece of something or it won't act like
other things okay got it the smallest
piece of things this is what science
teaches you we are translating a book
here called dupas Santa what's it
mean School of philosophy it's a study
of the school of philosophy Ben Kramer
is uh translating it we just slogged our
way through 22 Hindu
schools that died thousand years ago you
know and it drives you crazy you know
they all have different ideas and one of
them the vaja school of the James has
said that your soul is the size of a big
umbrella it's white it covers you from
the chest down when you get enlightened
it's 225,000 miles wide and and there
are there many many schools of thought
uh what's at the top is Nagina uh but
and the secret teachings are based on
Nagina and then so you go down from that
eight Buddhist schools groups and then
22 non- Buddhist schools that we study
that are still studi and Below those is
science okay what 30 schools
down uh 31 is
science It's A Primitive uh belief that
this is made of little pieces of stuff
uh glued together uh that are the
smallest uh functioning version of a
thing okay that belief is below uh the
lowest Hindu School in in the chart okay
in the
Seda why uh because the idea of an atom
is
crack there's something wrong with it
okay why an atom is the smallest
possible thing okay cannot be divided
further or it will lose its properties
okay so that means that every part of
the atom has to be Act the
same the left side must be acting the
same as the right side right if you
split them into left and right the left
side by itself cannot do its thing
that's means Adam and the right side by
itself cannot do its thing got it you
got to have an atom with a left side or
right side if you divide it it won't
work anymore this is science don't blame
me okay this is science and you believe
it you know
when I ask you what religion you are
your religion is cell phone come on you
know and it's spread to the whole world
the whole world believes in cell phone
and you can say I'm Muslim or I'm
Christian or I'm Buddhist I don't care
you're not really your cell phone you
know you are and I I travel constantly
we're going to Tokyo the day after
tomorrow then we go to Shenzhen then we
go to Vienna everyone is cell phone
religion
okay it doesn't matter what country
you're in and and they believe that
there's something in the copper that
carries electricity they believe that
you know there there's some quality in
the copper atom that the glass doesn't
have and that's why you make the wires
out of copper because they conduct
electricity okay got it so there's a
smallest piece of copper and it touches
another piece of copper G it you okay
this is what you were taught don't tell
me you don't believe it you do believe
it you just never think it then the the
copper atoms are nested together in the
wire and they have the ability to pass
electricity Pro electrons and
proton okay you believe that
and and they but you can't they're
they're like balls right each atam is
like a ball
okay if
you and you must have a whole atom for
it to work as copper agreed this is
science element that's the word element
okay got it are you okay nobody's
nodding but they have to sit together in
the same place and that's the only way
you can make a wire do you understand so
the left side of the copper atom which
is touching the right side of the copper
atom next to it has to act as if it were
the whole
atom okay which means the only way that
copper would ever work is if all the
atoms of copper in The Wire were in the
same
space nested like a Russian doll cogniz
way
huh matoska those dolls inside a doll
inside a doll okay that the for a cop
coer atom to work for copper atoms to
work together they must be occupying the
same space because if you only touch one
side of a copper atom it cannot act as a
copper atom because a copper atom split
in two cannot act as
copper something's weird like you resist
it I can see it you're like when do we
get
Refreshments no you're resisting you
don't want to hear it it's uncomfortable
for you I can tell you don't want to
think about it look G don't blame me it
was my chemistry teacher in high school
it's not what I I just never thought
about it but try to I'll say it
again if you split a copper atom it
doesn't act as copper anymore it cannot
carry electricity anymore okay which
means the whole atom must be doing
something okay if you if you only have
half of the atom it can't carry
electricity okay got it if you break an
atom in a acceler
it doesn't act as copper anymore that's
why it's called a copper atom and that's
why it's called an element and that's
why we call it the table periodic table
of the elements okay got
it so if you touch a part of the atom of
copper it cannot act as copper the whole
atom has to act together okay which
means that in a wire okay here's one
atom here's another atom they cannot be
side by side CU they won't work
cuz you only got the left side of one
and the right side of the other you
understand when you break it in half it
don't work anymore the left side of a
copper atom cannot act alone the whole
atom has to act which means that in a
copper wire all the items would have to
be inside all the other atoms and they'd
have to touch in every part of the atom
okay something weird is going on things
don't exist out there the way you
thought okay let me just tell you the
punchline in case you don't come back
after
refreshment
okay all right I I I I just in case you
leave okay you're like this guy's
cuckoo
uh there's a point to teaching people
this okay there's a point to it it's not
some weird philosophy if you understand
it uh you can make a a quarter billion
dollar company we sold it to Warren
Buffett uh it was a it was fun
okay and I don't know anything about
business nothing zero I was in a
monastery for 25 years he knows you were
there I didn't do anything I just
meditate and and wash
pots uh those are the two things we do
in the monastery I don't have any
business training uh but I know
Adams I know Nagina okay so I'll teach
in nag if in case you don't come back
okay ready now maybe some of you might
have seen this this
before I was in Singapore and some guy
came up to me and said uh he was angry
he okay wasn't from Singapore he from
another country I w't mention the
country but he talked like this and uh
he said Gila you are getting older I
said I know he said yeah but you don't
remember each year when you come to
Singapore you teach the same thing and
we pay again I said what's wrong with
that
and I said I didn't forget I want you to
understand it he but I understood the
first time I said are you successful
well I'm not real successful then you
didn't understand it okay okay got it I
think I can do the same thing in this
room by the way if you are a Buddhist
and I don't care if you're a Buddhist
but if you are a Buddhist okay there's
another reason why I teach it over and
over again okay if you understand the
five paths Theory which are explained in
a certain
Mantra if you understand that five path
okay the second path is understanding
the pen okay uh and there's four parts
of the second path if you get the
jam if you reach a a strong
understanding of the pen according to
Buddhism okay not me you cannot go to
hell or become an animal after you die
it's not possible okay okay it and we're
going to talk more about it later
somewhere uh if you understand this
clearly you are protected after you die
so you know I don't tell that to
business audiences but I keep telling
them to pen over and over again okay CU
you're really protecting someone if you
understand it clearly it's not possible
to go to a bad place after you die so
you know I used to work for an Israeli
company and the owner was Israeli right
they two owners and uh I used to go so
my salary I used to take a little bit
for shoes and and food and stuff and
then I would donate the rest of the
monastery and so every six months I'd go
in and and we would calculate how much
they owe the monastery and then he'd say
Let me throw in another
100,000 he would often say like that let
me throw in another 100,000 you know I'm
like cool you you know and then it got
to be a thing you know like every time I
went to get the check every 6 months
he'd be like I'd be
like okay I'll throw in 150,000 you know
I'm like damn you know and then I'd go
home to my llama you know RI it would be
the day and he'd be waiting at the door
he'd say what he throw in I'd say 150 go
you
know and uh one day I asked him you know
like after 10 years I'm like can I ask
you a personal question he says yeah
yeah I said you're Israeli you know
you're all Jewish you're 100% Jewish
country you know and uh can I just ask
you why you throwing 100,000 why you
throwing 150,000 to a Buddhist Monastery
you know I'm face to face with him and
I'm like and I was I'm a little afraid
to ask the questions because I didn't
want him thinking about it too
much but I'm
like why do you do that for another
religion he says look you know I'm a
practical guy you never know who's
[Music]
right you know you better give it
donations you know give some donations
to different places you know so learn
the pen okay if it's a 1% chance that
I'm right and you won't go to a bad
place after you
die what's a big deal it takes five
minutes you know cover your what do you
call cover your uh
basis uh okay if it's true you just got
a cosmic
guarantee about your next life you know
and if it's wrong you know you just
delayed your Refreshments for five
minutes okay so let's do that and then
we'll take a break okay so uh I'll ask
question you give answer and I always
tell people don't be like Scott doesn't
like me to mention the company because
they get upset when they hear about it
a large International Airline in England
uh and we went and solved one of their
management Pro we taught the nine vice
presidents okay and I said give me an
answer I'm going to ask you questions
give me an answer you know I said what's
this thing and they're like
this I said no no just tell me what it I
don't know something about this island
country uh where they're too polite to
answer something I don't know what it is
what is this thing yeah it's a pen okay
now second question just answer me okay
I'm trying to save you trouble later on
maybe cover your bases Okay then if a
little dog comes in here and I
go what will the dog do with
that yeah they old Che it uh question
does a dog see a
pen they don't see this as a pen uh I
used to ask Francis all these questions
but I'm bored of asking you because you
always answer
correctly we should ask your dad cuz he
doesn't know the
answers uh who's right the human or the
dog both are right it's not a big thing
right the dog can chew I met one guy in
Florida who swore the human was right
and the dog was wrong so I'm not talking
I'm not saying anything about Florida
but in the whole world that's the only
guy and uh
so
anyway now now we go to emptiness okay
you heard the word emptiness many times
you have weird ideas about it they're
all wrong okay so here's the real
meaning of
emptiness okay
Tom and don't just relax and learn it
okay and forget everything else you ever
heard because it's all
okay here's I put this here
okay the dogss go out the humans go out
at that time is this a pen or a
chw yeah it's nothing that's emptiness
there's no other meaning of emptiness
you know I've translated I believe more
than any other
human uh I believe so I me Arts except
for art he's always giving me trouble
but uh you know it doesn't all the
ancient scriptures don't say anything
more than that okay I mean we'll keep
translating them cuz it's
fun and we need your financial help but
anyway uh there's nothing more than that
okay it's it's empty when the dark's
gone and the human's gone and that's the
only meaning of emptiness it's available
to be something but it's nothing yet
okay it has a potential that's called
emptiness no crying
just kidding
now now I lost
my yeah if the okay so the human comes
back in right and the human approaches
the stool and looks down at that moment
what does this thing
become yeah it becomes a pen so the next
question is easy does the pen come from
the pen or does the pen come from me
it must be coming from me because if a
dog preceded me into the room it would
have become
a CH toy that proves dependent
origination forget the word forget all
that I don't know who invented this
English translation it's a national
disaster like some other
people uh okay you come
in uh and and at that moment that I look
down it becomes a pen because of that
it's got to be coming from me somehow
okay then how does it come from me when
I first catch s of it a seed opens in my
mind a karmic seed opens in my mind the
seed splits open in 165th of a second a
an image comes out of a pen which is
this big okay an image this big comes
out of the karma karma means mental seed
right comes out of the seed the seed
cracks open a picture comes out and it
goes on the
pieces that's a clue about the
cracks okay it goes onto the pieces and
makes them into a pen okay the dog has
different seeds when their seed cracks
open a picture of a chw toy comes out
and goes on the same Parts okay it's the
same Parts okay and those that by the
way well that's another story what if I
have dog seeds and not human
seeds yeah I'll see this as a PA how
long does it take to re born to be
reborn as a
dog it takes 165th of a second this BTO
stuff was for lower school okay 49 days
in the B please do prayers
gisha no it takes 65th of a second you
see a new seat opens and you see
something else you see what I mean it's
coming from me the the pen is coming
from me okay how ah
Tim quick then we'll give them a break
they're getting tired I can tell okay
this is called the $100
thing that lady back there is totally
innocent uh
okay how to plant a seed four steps
don't forget it it's expensive for me to
teach it please stand up what's your
name Denise Denise okay Denise is gonna
help me make a video look at it this
week three
times okay I yeah go ahead no it's okay
oh on you uh quarter billion do dollar
thing okay understand okay and you know
I asked people in China to film it just
film it if you're in a good mood it
takes 2 minutes okay and then look at it
three times this week and you will never
have financial problems again in your
life forget that people will keep giving
you money it's it's really
weird okay and your secretary will call
you and say the bank account's going
crazy give it
away okay here we go uh planting the
seed that opened into the create the pen
takes four steps okay just just learn
them okay you never know who's
right okay it doesn't cost you anything
just try it okay step number one decide
what you want as a goal I'm using money
because it's measurable okay I can claim
to be the happiest person in this room
but I can't prove it right money I can
prove so it's just something countable
okay so decide what you want in your
life choose one thing let's say I want
money okay I want to guess wants to make
$1,000 out of1 this is how I make my
living he's giving away these things
you're laugh but it's
true I want to turn this into $1,000
within 10 days or something like that
okay so that's my goal step number one
Define your goals step number two you
must have a partner to plant the seed
with you cannot plant a seed without a
partner it's not possible you must plant
a seed with another person Denise Denise
Denise so you got to ask her will you
help me plant this Karma yes yes okay so
you got to find somebody else who wants
the same thing that you want do you want
to make some money tonight free money
okay so we made a deal step number two
she's my karmic partner now tonight okay
step number three do something to help
her that relates to your goal
okay so she's going to put her hand out
like this okay and and I'm going to step
three is where you plant the seed step
three is where you plant the seed I put
the money in her hand and I close the
hand now watch
one
two three
dting and I plant a SE okay how do I
plant a you you can
relax uh and good people chase me to the
stage trying to give it back to me
trying to thwart my seed planting I'm
like stop go away keep it
okay how did I plant the karma what does
karma mean Karma means my mental tape
recorder my mental recorder saw me open
my hand and that image came into my
brain and touched my mind and left an
imprint on my mind okay got it and and
that's a karma that's a sin that
impression on my mind created by the
image of my hand opening as I saw it
makes an impression on my mind okay and
that's a karma that's the meaning of
ye okay that's karma that's how you
plant Karma okay you must help another
person okay so that seed is in my mind
cool step four okay everyone in this
room has done countless kind things to
other people in their life everybody in
this room has made karma karma doubles
every 24 hours it multiplies like cancer
virus it it it splits like an amoeba
every 24 hours you should be rich by now
you know everyone gave money to somebody
right and you should be rich n but the
problem is a seed will not open unless
it gets watered it's just like a tree
seed the water is okay secret practice
every night before you go to bed when
you lay your head down on the pillow
think to yourself of all the sweet
things you did for other people today if
you didn't do anything nice today think
of something you did yesterday if you
didn't do anything nice all week think
of last week if you didn't do anything
nice all year think of last year if you
didn't do anything you understand karmic
seed cannot be destroyed once I open my
hand and once I see my hand open a seed
is planted in my mind it cannot be
destroyed it must come back it must come
back it must open but it may take a
hundred
years okay so there's a way to water it
which is before you go to sleep think of
the kind things you did today and be
happy just be happy okay if you didn't
do anything at all your whole
life be happy about what somebody else
did okay but but never go to sleep
thinking something negative okay
always control your mind what is that
called by the way when you fight with
your mind your mind wants to think about
money problems relationship problems job
problems president
problems your mind wants to do that but
you fight you must fight just before you
go to sleep because then your mind will
cook the seed all all night okay what's
that fight
called it's called meditation that's
meditation fight with your own mind your
mind wants to think about problems I got
problems my boss yell at me my husband
said something night my kids don't
listen to me they just play
baseball I mean stop thinking about
problems before sleep at breakfast think
about your problems cuz problems get
smaller when the daylight comes okay
before you go as you go to bed you must
think about something good you did okay
and then that will cook all night in
your mind okay and and that's how to
make money okay that's all if you don't
do it the seed will sit there and you
already have millions of seeds in your
mind okay so for God's sake tonight or
in this lecture as you fall
asleep just before you W up think about
something good you
did okay and that fees the seed it fees
the seed and then the seed will grow
fast and and and frankly you can have
incredible financial success I I can't
even describe JB and I were trying to
raise $5 million right for uh the
college
endowment and we just planted seeds and
uh we made the first payment uh two
weeks
ago uh about a million dollars uh it
just comes okay just try it don't
be cover your
basis you know the worst thing that
happens is you give someone $100 okay uh
the best thing that happens
is by the way the old way of making
money has cracks in
it okay that's what I'm trying to say
you work hard hard hard some people work
hard and make money some people do the
same thing and
don't make money some people don't work
at all and get money some people don't
work at all and stay
poor there's s there's a crack there
didn't you ever wonder about it here
these lazy idiot people become reach
high
positions or get lots of money and then
other people who are deserving and
sensitive and intelligent uh lose lose
you know they don't get didn't it ever
seem strange to
you like didn't you think something
might be
wrong you see if you see a crack in the
window tell somebody you see and do
something you see what I mean that's
what we're talking about tonight so this
is a new model of airplane it has
rounded Windows which is why all
airplanes now have rounded windows and
uh just try it cover your
basis okay uh try
so what really makes a copper atom
work is that uh okay this is weird Okay
if you give away money to
people and if you do your meditation
before you sleep okay and it's fun
anyway because it's no fun to go to
sleep with thinking about your problems
okay so it's a good habit to get in the
habit when you put your head on your
pill control your mind fight with your
mind that fight is called meditation
that's all meditation is you know I'm
not going to think about my problems
with my boss or my wife or or or my kids
I'm going to think about anything I did
good today okay then that
uh it brings Prana to the seed and then
the seed will open faster okay and if
you don't do that but the seeds will
open at
random you know without control stuff
you did to your little brother when you
were six years old will ripen first no I
mean
uh you can control the priority of which
seeds open if you use this technique of
as you fall asleep you think about sweet
things you've done for other people
okay uh and then and then the seeds will
open fast and I it's my life is very
frustrating because I go around the
world teaching people how to be
successful I guess what percent do it 5%
10% do it they get crazy
results and then other people just kind
of drift away and I never see him again
and I don't know I was thinking to take
my clothes off or
something uh to get your attention but
uh
you got to try just try it once okay
don't it doesn't cost anything right uh
just give it a try okay pick something
you want to happen and then do those
four steps okay number one this is what
I would like to happen it could be uh I
I would like to find a a romantic
partner okay John Brady came to me I
don't
know wait we won't talk about
that uh no so I want a partner I want a
beautiful partner number one number two
well you need to find someone else who
who's lonely okay that's number two then
you have to do something with them to
make them not be lonely and you know I
went out with my old lady I have an old
lady uh I took her out uh yesterday day
before and we we went to the a nice
restaurant Vincent Bistro it's like the
one of the nicer French restaurants in
Phoenix and uh we sat down they have a
special
croissant and they let you eat as many
as you want and I told the guy did you
ever have anybody just eat the croissant
and get up and walk out and he said you
would be the second
one so uh and she ate like five of them
and then she started to get sick she's
94 uh V's mom and uh she got really sick
and we had to get her up I'm paying the
bill while I'm carrying her out and and
but what I'm saying is you got to find
an an elderly person you help them you
take them out to Vincent once a month
don't let them meat the
cant and
uh that's step number three okay do
something nice to them on on a regular
basis okay
and then uh be happy about it at night
think about it at night before you go to
sleep okay and that's all and because
the atom of copper is coming from you
okay it cannot be what it seems to be
the scientists are wrong okay copper
doesn't act like copper because copper
cannot act like copper because atoms of
copper don't act like copper unless the
whole atom is acting but the whole atom
can't touch another atom because they're
balls and they can only touch on one
part of an atom if only a part of an
atom can touch it can't do
anything understand it's not true what
they told you in school so learn a new
learn a new idea of where the world
comes from and try to notice the cracks
you know try to notice that things you
try don't work okay like go to business
school pay Harvard I don't
know what is
it I don't know we taught at MIT
business school they charge a lot and uh
you know they'll teach you marketing and
they'll teach you accounting and they'll
teach you a dozen things you know and
then they'll give you a degree and then
maybe you will fail and maybe you will
succeed and you can see that with your
own eyes it's not that 100% of people
who went to Harvard Business School are
successful they're not it doesn't work
because what they're teaching is
incorrect because Adams can't do what
they
do okay don't sit in a plane with square
windows
and and say wow there's cracks in the
window what do you
think you know try try to ask question
what's really happening okay and uh
what's really happening
is that the pen has Parts it has a top
and it has a bottom and when you put the
parts together it's not a pen
yet okay because a dog doesn't see a pen
if it was a pen when you put the top and
the bottom together then a dog would see
a pen try to understand okay uh the fact
that the dog doesn't the fact that the
dog shoes on it and that the fact that
your mouth doesn't water when I hold it
up proves that it's not coming from its
own side and and this is the garina and
the garina sounds very uh confusing the
garina is either on Aid or he's right
you see there's nothing between like his
the things he says are crazy look top of
pen bottom of pen put together no pen
why do don't see
pen that's all that's
all okay something else must be
happening okay your whole
uh opinion of where the world is coming
from is cracked and you
gotta someone you came to Lincoln Center
small Auditorium I don't tell them the
smaller time people asked me where were
you yesterday I was like I was like just
teaching at Lincoln Center you know and
uh
and uh and then I also didn't say that I
had to pay for it but anyway
uh but there's small cracks in your life
and that's why things don't happen the
way you want them to you see that's why
you don't have a lot of money or that's
why you don't have a perfect
relationship or that's why you have
health problems or that's why your
mind's not peaceful or that's why you
have a weird political things going on
okay it's all coming from you okay so
don't blame other people um try to
notice that the things you try to do to
make other things happen don't work just
admit it okay I so my students I've
never owned a new car in my life and my
students bought me one
recently okay
so you
know I don't have time to drive it
anyway I think I've driven it like three
times but uh they bought me a beautiful
new car they painted it they spent a lot
of money to paint it my favorite color
sky blue and uh you know and it's weird
because it doesn't have a key anymore
and I'm always looking for the key and I
said just push the button and I said but
anybody could push the button and
they're like don't worry about it you
know so listen try to understand try to
understand and then we'll then it's
enough tonight okay then you take the
four steps recording home and you get
rich take me out to a restaurant next
year
uh pushing the button doesn't start the
car why cuz it
doesn't
always
work okay that means it never started
the car okay try to this is now I'm
pretending to be the Garder the Arya
okay I'm pretending to be in the Garder
okay try to grasp that there's something
weird going on with cars you know or a
light okay the
light does the light always turn on when
you flip the switch you come home you go
like this on the wall
thing does it always work
no I mean sometimes the light burns out
it goes poop and you know then you're
like digging around in the dark under
the sink in the bathroom to try to find
the light bulbs come on you did
it
okay it doesn't always work now if I'm
the guarder sitting here right now if
I'm the Arya sitting here right now I
will say that
proves that there's no
connection between turning the light
switch and the light going on
that proves that turning the light
switch doesn't make the light go on and
pushing the button in your new car
doesn't make the engine start because it
doesn't always make the engine start and
you're like d come on sometimes the
battery's dead you know stuff happens
okay but if I'm the guarder okay I'm
said there's a crack there if it doesn't
start if the light doesn't go on
it proves there's no connection between
the button and the car starting well
guess you know just
tap
$500 forget it you don't know this one
even my students in s Dona don't own
this one you shut
up wait tell me again tell me again wait
say it
again that's incorrect
[Music]
I lost 3,000 bucks to him
recently I bet on a safe one he's the
human
dictionary I hate
you uh yeah he walked away with 3,000
bucks one night but not
tonight uh tap means okay suppose just
suppose in the theoretical case okay in
the theoretical case that you're right
gisha you know so so okay the pushing
the button doesn't start the car so what
then does start the
car a picture coming out of my mind
starts the car in the same way that a
picture coming out of my mind creates a
pen that's all it's that simple okay
there's a small picture of a starting
car coming out of here onto the parts
okay there is Adam Parts there's a left
side there's a right side but if you
want it to act like copper you got to
have copper atom
seeds in your mind from helping other
people to communicate who are having
trouble
communicating that's why copper acts
like Copper got it because it cannot act
like copper if it's atoms because the
left side won't act like copper and the
left side can only touch the right side
of the next atom and the back end of the
next atom isn't touching the front end
atom so it can't be
acting like copper
okay got it a phone works because you
have friends who are arguing who are
married and you help them
communicate and if you don't do that
your phone won't
work okay and if you don't give rides
with your
car if you're selfish and you take all
the world's oil for your
country your cars won't work okay your
cars will die your cars won't start okay
got it and the whole reality is based on
kindness to other people reality itself
Adams work if you're nice to people and
Adams don't work if you're not nice to
people because the pen is coming from
you okay and we just proved it nobody in
the room had a problem with it with the
pen some people had a problem with the
Copper at them I'm
sorry okay everything's coming from how
you treat other people so all this Jesus
stuff and Buddha stuff and Muhammad
stuff it's all that you see they want
you to be successful they're like be
nice to other people take care of other
people do things for other people give
rides to other people your car will
always start or people will give you
cars you don't have to fight and work
for a year to to buy a new car okay just
help other people get somewhere because
the car is coming from you because the
parts don't work there's some cracks in
there that idea that idea doesn't work
okay and and be smart play your what do
you
call
um cover your
basis cover your
basis okay if someone comes
along look up jewelry.com that name cost
$21 million we own it I mean the company
own own jewelry.com okay no business
training no understanding of anything
never touched a diamond in my life okay
up to
starting but I know
nard okay it just learn just give it a
try cover your basis right it's not not
so hard do the force what's the worst
thing that can happen Denise gets
Rich okay you made somebody else happy
if this whole stuff doesn't
work the worst thing you did was give
another person a ride or or you gave
someone you helped someone financially
you took an old lady to the
restaurant next time she's not going to
eat all the croissants okay and the
worst thing that can happen is that
you're nice to somebody else okay it the
but if what I'm saying is true then
reality is Flowing from
here and it comes from being kind to
other people and helping other people
okay and and you cover your basis just
try it okay try to
notice that the way you're doing things
now doesn't always
work okay it you know that since you're
a kid you know that what you try you
know that and you you don't question it
anymore but fix it okay wouldn't it be
nice if everything you tried work you
know you try to have a relationship with
somebody or you you try to make some
money or or you try to get skinny or
healthy and wouldn't it be nice if uh
everything you ever
tried work okay but that means you have
to notice
that what you tried so far doesn't
always work and then you have to
question copper
atoms okay so try the four steps
okay Scott and me where's Scott yeah we
were in Shanghai okay last thing then I
got to go They're Gonna they're G to
threaten me again uh we were in Shanghai
and this guy came up to me and said okay
I have I want to try the four steps I
said okay try I said I was waving
goodbye I said what do you what do you
want he said I want $10 million this
year I said okay try four steps
okay next year he's waiting outside you
were there I think he's like
bodyguarding me back to the room and you
know he's like this tall and uh and the
guy's waiting for me at the door and
he's agitated and he and he jams into
the elevator with me and I'm like and
he's like it didn't work and I'm like
what he's said this voice death didn't
work you know so I know how to respond
to that
uh you you say did you do step number
one well first I have to tell you in the
diamond business one of the first things
they teach you is how to tell if a
person's
lying when you're doing a negotiation so
I negotiated many many deals every day
that was my job and they teach you the
signs of a person who's going to lie and
they look down first or they move
something on the table they'll move a
pen or they'll so watch for these two
things with your kids
especially so just before they I mean
not that they
lie but they their eyes will go down
just a sec you know like this so I'm
watching his eyes I said did you do step
number one what is Step number one he
said I want it's a goal I want $10
million I said okay that's he didn't
look down I did did you do step number
two which is
what did you find a partner did you find
a kic partner and his eyes didn't move
he said I did it's another guy who does
import export from China you know and I
said good did you do step number three
and he's holding my
eyes yeah I'm checking I'm holding his
eyes and he says I did I helped him once
a week one hour what you said I helped
him then I I said did you do do step
number four because it's always step
number four it's always step number four
cuz people have a problem with thinking
good thoughts before they go to bed
check it out tonight
okay I'm looking I'm holding his eyes
and I said did you every night for two
minutes think about helping this guy and
what a nice thing you're doing and he
goes mostly and I'm like get out of here
you know I said just go away talk to me
next year do step number four that's the
most common thing I don't know why
people don't like to admit that they did
something nice I'm not talking Pride I'm
talking just be honest with yourself I
helped somebody today it's honest and
you have to do that okay so he looks
down and I said okay I'm getting off the
elevator I'll see you you know but
that's why it didn't work and he looks
at me and he says he's more agitated he
says I didn't say it didn't work I said
but you say you didn't get the $10
million yeah I only got
eight and I'm Scott Scott and me are
like I'm like I wish I had this guy's
problem he's like yeah and uh but when
you're a teacher you have to be okay you
have to be really tough on you have to
say I can't believe you didn't do number
four you know you lose $2 million cuz
you're too lazy when you go to bed you
know what's wrong with you and he's like
oh I'm so sorry I'll do better next year
you know and uh next year I he was
waiting for me at the elevator he goes
he goes he
goes I said
okay do it okay thank you uh try to
notice that your life's crack otherwise
there's weird weird things are happening
things don't start when they're supposed
to start you know things they tell you
in business school don't work sometimes
so try to be a little try to notice
what's going on and don't be
satisfied with planes that fall apart
like try to notice that things don't
work the way you thought they did try
the new way cover your bases it doesn't
cost too much just try it and I say it
will work okay cool thank you okay